[{"question":"Which one of the following traits of garden pea studied by Mendel, was a recessive feature?","a":"Round seed shape","b":"Axial flower position","c":"Green seed colour","d":"Green pod colour","hint":"","correct":"c"},{"question":"In a certain plant, red fruit (R) is dominant over yellow fruit (r) and tallness (T) is dominant over shortness (t). If a plant with RRTt genotype is crossed with a plant irtt genotype, what will be the percentage of tall plants with red fruits in the progeny?","a":"50%","b":"100%","c":"75%","d":"25%","hint":"","correct":"a"},{"question":"Suppose that in sheep, a dominant allele (B) produces black hair and a recessive allele (b) produces white hair. If you saw a black sheep, you would be able to identify:","a":"Its phenotype for hair colour.","b":"Its genotype for hair colour.","c":"The genotypes for only one of its parents.","d":"The genotypes for both of its parents.","hint":"","correct":"a"},{"question":"Mendel's rules do not correctly predict patterns of inheritance for tightly linked genes or the inheritance of alleles that show incomplete dominance or epistasis. Does this mean that his hypothesis are incorrect?","a":"Yes, because they are relevant to only a small number of organisms and traits.","b":"Yes, because not all data support his hypothesis.","c":"No, because he was not aware of meiosis or the chromosome theory of inheritance.","d":"No, it just means that his hypothesis are limited to certain conditions.","hint":"","correct":"d"},{"question":"In the F2 generation of a dihybrid cross between yellow, round seeded and green, wrinkled seeded pea plants, 17 out of 254 pea seeds were green and wrinkled. Other seeds were: Yellow and round; green and round; yellow and wrinkled. These results indicate which of the Following statements ?","a":"Crossing over has occurred.","b":"Green and wrinkled are both recessive characters.","c":"The alleles for green and wrinkled are linked.","d":"The allele for green is recessive but not the allele for wrinkled.","hint":"","correct":"b"},{"question":"The F2 generation of a cross produced identical phenotypic and genotypic ratio. It is not an expected Mendelian result, and can be attributed to:","a":"Independent assortment","b":"Linkage","c":"Incomplete dominance","d":"None of the above","hint":"","correct":"c"},{"question":"The total number of progeny obtained through dihybrid cross of Mendel is 1280 in F, generation. How many of them are recombinants?","a":"240","b":"360","c":"480","d":"720","hint":"","correct":"c"},{"question":"Which of the following is not a hereditary disease?","a":"Cystic fibrosis ","b":"Thalassemia","c":"Haemophilia","d":"Cretinism","hint":"","correct":"d"},{"question":"A women with 47 chromosomes due to three copies of chromosome 21 is characterised by:","a":"Superfemaleness ","b":"Triploidy","c":"Turner's Syndrome","d":"Down's Syndrome","hint":"","correct":"a"},{"question":"A modified dihybrid mendelian ratio of 9: 3: 4 indicates:","a":"Supplementary genes","b":"Complementary genes","c":"Lethal genes","d":"Epistatic genes","hint":"","correct":"a"},{"question":"A modified dihybrid mendelian ratio of 9: 3: 4 indicates:","a":"Supplementary genes","b":"Complementary genes","c":"Lethal genes","d":"Epistatic genes","hint":"","correct":"c"},{"question":"In multiple allele system, a gamete possesses:","a":"Several alleles","b":"Two Alleles","c":"Three Alleles","d":"One Allele Critical Thinking ","hint":"","correct":"a"},{"question":"Which mendelian principle will not operate if two genes under study are close together?","a":"Paired unit factors","b":"Dominace","c":"Segregation","d":"Independent assortment","hint":"","correct":"d"},{"question":"The person with Turner's syndrome has:","a":"45 autosomes and X sex chromosome","b":"44 autosomes and XYY sex chromosomes","c":"45 autosomes and XYY sex chromosomes","d":"44 autosomes and X sex chromosome","hint":"","correct":"d"},{"question":"Mongolism, Edward's syndrome and Patau's syndrome are due to:","a":"Autosomal abnormalities ","b":"Allosomal Abnormalities","c":"Both (a) and (b) ","d":"None Of The Above","hint":"","correct":"d"},{"question":"Albinism and phenylketonuria are disorders due to:","a":"Recessive autosomal genes","b":"Dominant Autosomal Genes ","c":"Recessive Sex Genes","d":"Dominant Sex Genes","hint":"","correct":"a"},{"question":"In Klinefelter's syndrome, the sex chromosome compliment is:","a":"22AA+ XXY ","b":"22AA + XO","c":"22AA+ XY","d":"22AA + XX","hint":"","correct":"a"},{"question":"Which of the following is related to heart diseases?","a":"Turner's syndrome ","b":"Edward's Syndrome ","c":"Cushing's Syndrome","d":"Patau's Syndrome","hint":"","correct":"d"},{"question":"In Drosophila XXY represents a female but in human it is an abnormal male. It shows that:","a":"Y-chromosome is essential for male sex in human.","b":"Y-chromosome is essential for female sex determination in Drosophila.","c":"Y-chromosome is not essential for male sex determination in human.","d":"All of the above","hint":"","correct":"a"},{"question":"Which of the following statements regarding crossing-over is incorrect?","a":"Crossing-over disrupts the linkage between genes on the same chromosome.","b":"Crossing-over disrupts the linkage between genes on different chromosomes.","c":"Crossing-over produces new genetic combinations.","d":"Crossing-over produces non-parental chromosomes.","hint":"","correct":"b"},{"question":"Drosophila flies with XXY genotype are females but in case of humans, such individuals are abnormal males (Klinefelter's syndrome). This indicates that:","a":"The Y chromosome has no role in sex determination.","b":"In Drosophila, the Y chromosome is essential for sex determination.","c":"The Y chromosome is male determining in humans.","d":"The Y chromosome is female determining in Drosophila.","hint":"","correct":"c"},{"question":"Christmas disease is another name of:","a":"Sleeping sickness ","b":"Haemophilia","c":"Hepatitis B","d":"Down's Svndrome","hint":"","correct":"b"},{"question":"Barr-body (seen in saliva test in Olympic games) is associated with:","a":" Y-chromosome ","b":"X-chromosome","c":"Autosome","d":"Male Sex Only","hint":"","correct":"b"},{"question":"The males of grasshoppers and bugs possess two sets of autosomes and:","a":"Only Y-chromosome","b":"Only X-chromosome","c":"X and Y-chromosome","d":"Neither X nor Y-chromosome","hint":"","correct":"b"},{"question":"Which of the following match is correct?","a":"Sickel cell anaemia - X-chromosome","b":"Down Syndrome - 21 chromosome","c":"Parkinsonism - XY chromosome","d":"Haemophilia - Y chromosome","hint":"","correct":"b"},{"question":"There are three genes a, b, c. Percentage of crossing over between a and b is 20%, b and c is 28% an a and c is 8%. What is the sequence of genes on chromosome?","a":"b, a, c","b":"A, B, C","c":"a, c, b ","d":"None Of These","hint":"","correct":"a"},{"question":"Human skin colour is controlled by several gene cal king ween pairs. Let us assume here that there are just three gene pairs on different chromosomes and that for each pair there are two alleles, an incompletely dominant one that codes for melanin deposition ween and an incompletely recessive one that codes for no melanin deposition. If a very dark skinned netic person marries a very light skinned woman, what will be the chance that their offspring will ental have very dark skin?","a":"1/64 ","b":" 1/4","c":" 5/8","d":"9/64","hint":"","correct":"a"},{"question":"Rh factor is responsible for which of the following disease?","a":"AIDS ","b":"Turner's Syndrome","c":"Erythroblastosis foetalis ","d":"Sickle -Cell Anaemia","hint":"","correct":"c"},{"question":"Repeated selfing produces:","a":"Heterozygosity ng in (b)","b":" Homozygosity ","c":" Homozygosity in some and heterozygosity ining in other traits","d":"Pure hybrids","hint":"","correct":"b"},{"question":"In genetics, the term test cross means:","a":"the crossing of F, individual with homozygous recessive.","b":"crossing an F, individual with either of the two parents.","c":"crossing F, individual with another F, individual.","d":"crossing F, individual with that of Fz.","hint":"","correct":"a"},{"question":"In Mendelian dihybrid cross, when heterozygous round yellow are self crossed, round green offsprings are produced which are represented by genotype?","a":"RrYy, RrYY, RRYy","b":"RrYY, RRyy, rryy","c":"rrY y, rrY Y","d":"RRyy, Rryy","hint":"","correct":"d"},{"question":"Which of the following illustrates pleiotropy?","a":"In fruit flies, the genes for scarlet eyes and hairy body are located on the same chromosome.","b":"Matings between earless sheep and long-eared sheep always result in short-eared offspring.","c":"Wheat kernels can range from white to red cky in color, a trait controlled by several genes.","d":"The human cystic fibrosis gene causes many symptoms, from respiratory distress To Digestive problem","hint":"","correct":"d"},{"question":"A pea plant with purple flowers is heterozygous for flower colour. Its genotype is Pp. The P and p alleles in the pea plant's cells are located:","a":"nextto each other on the same chromosome.","b":"at the same location on homologous chromosomes.","c":"on the X and Y chromosomes.","d":"some distance apart on the same chromosome.","hint":"","correct":"b"},{"question":"Consider a gene that has two alleles and shows complete dominance. When two heterozygotes for this gene breed, they have a 25% chance of producing a homozygous recessive offspring. The next time they breed, what are the chances that they will once again have a homozygous recessive progeny?","a":"0%","b":"25%","c":"75%","d":"100%","hint":"","correct":"b"},{"question":"When dominant and recessive alleles express percentag, itself together it is called______ .","a":"codominance ","b":"Dominance","c":"Amphidominace","d":"Pseudodominance","hint":"","correct":"a"},{"question":"The genes controlling the seven pea characters Parent studied by Mendel are now known to be located on how many different chromosomes?","a":"Four","b":"Seven","c":"Six","d":"Five","hint":"","correct":"a"},{"question":"The genes controlling the seven pea characters Parent studied by Mendel are now known to be located on how many different chromosomes?","a":"Four","b":"Seven","c":"Six","d":"Five","hint":"","correct":"a"},{"question":"Barr body is found in: ","a":"Male Somatic Cells","b":"Male Germinal Cells","c":"Female somatic cells","d":"Female germinal cells","hint":"","correct":"c"},{"question":"Barr body is found in: ","a":"Male Somatic Cells","b":"Male Germinal Cells","c":"Female somatic cells","d":"Female germinal cells","hint":"","correct":"c"},{"question":"Which of the following chromosome arrangement is symbolised by 2n + 2?","a":"Tetraploid ","b":"Nullisomic","c":"Trisomic","d":" Tetrasomic","hint":"","correct":"d"},{"question":"Sickle cell anaemia is:","a":"caused by substitution of valine by glutamic acid in the beta globin chain of haemoglobin.","b":"caused by a change in a single base pair of DNA.","c":"characterised by elongated sickle like RBCs with a nucleus.","d":"an autosomal linked dominant trait.","hint":"","correct":"b"}]